Guide to the Eliot Katz Papers TAM.722
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Eliot Katz Papers
1975-2017
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Katz, Eliot
TAM.722
3.25 Linear Feet in 2 record cartons, 2 manuscript boxes, and 1 oversize folder in a shared box
4.79 Gigabytes
6 videocassettes (vhs)
The Eliot Katz Papers (1975-2017) includes essays, reports, newspaper clippings, photographs, personal writings, poetry and prose, and memorabilia related to Katz's activities as an activist and poet. The collection also contains correspondence between Katz and the poet Allen Ginsberg, which documents the influences in Katz’s career as a poet and activist of human rights. A significant portion of the collection consists of correspondence with other major activists and writers like Abbie Hoffman, Charles Bukowski, Adrienne Rich, Dave Dellinger, Tom Waits, and Amiri Baraka. As an advocate for homeless individuals and families of Central New Jersey, Katz dedicated himself to work with the Middlesex Interfaith Partners with the Homeless (MIPH) to institute housing and food programs. The collection also features newspaper clippings of poetry reviews and political events; photographs taken at literary events and political rallies; event posters to a variety of poetry readings; and memorabilia relating to his career as an activist and poet are also present in the collection. Of particular significance, the collection also features drafts and original manuscripts of Katz’s poetry and other published works.
Scope and Contents
The Eliot Katz Papers contains correspondence between Katz and Allen Ginsberg, as well as with major activists and writers like Abbie Hoffman, Charles Bukowski, Adrienne Rich, Dave Dellinger, Tom Waits, and Amiri Baraka. The collection also includes newspaper clippings of poetry reviews and political events; photographs taken at literary events and political rallies; event posters to a variety of poetry readings; and memorabilia relating to Katz's career as an activist and poet. Of particular significance, the collection also includes drafts and original manuscripts of Katz’s poetry and other published works. The collection also contains video recordings of interviews with Katz in addition to electronic recordings of Katz's poetry activites.
Biographical Note
Eliot Katz (1957- ) is an American poet and activist. In the fall of 1976, as a student of Rutgers University, Katz met the prominent writer Allen Ginsberg. Over time, Katz developed a relationship with and became Ginsberg’s apprentice. His interest in human rights causes and poetry was influenced greatly by Ginsberg. As a longtime resident of New Brunswick, New Jersey, Katz worked with Middlesex Interfaith Partners with the Homeless (MIPH) as an advocate for homeless families and individuals. He was a cofounder and former editor of Long Shot literary magazine, and his poems appear in numerous anthologies including,Blue Stones and Salt Hay: An Anthology of Contemporary New Jersey Poets, and Aloud: Voices from the Nuyorican Poets Cafe. He is the author of books of poetry, including:Space and Other Poems for Love, Laughs, and Social Transformation, Unlocking the Exits: Poems, Les voleurs au travail/Thieves at Work, and coeditor of Poems for the Nation: A Collection of Contemporary Political Poems. Katz currently resides in Hoboken, New Jersey.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Eliot Katz in September, October, and November of 2017. The accession numbers associated with this gift are 2017.056 and 2017.079.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Advance notice is required for the use of computer records. Original physical digital media is restricted. Born-digital materials have not been transferred and may not be available to researchers. Researchers may request access copies. To request that material be transferred, or if you are unsure if material has been transferred, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
American poetry -- 20th century.; United States -- Politics and government -- 20th century -- Poetry; Homelessness -- New Jersey; Correspondence.; Scrapbooks.; War poetry.; Anti-war poetry; Ginsberg, Allen, 1926-1997
- Political Poetry Lecture Notes - Recto/Verso, late 1990s (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Howard Zinn Emails, 2002-2006 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Articles on E.K. or book since SPACE, 1986-1995 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Posters for Recent E.K. Readings, mid 1990s (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Adrienne Rich File, 2003-2012 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Notes received regarding 2007 Chapbooks [?] or Howl Essay, 2005-2007 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Pro-Democracy Art Project, 1987-1990 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- BPC Tribute to Allen Ginsberg to Benefit Alternative Media, 2003-05-03 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Letters, 1998-2007 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Letters, 1988-2003 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Essays, Articles, Letters, 1994-1997 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Coffee House Press, 1994-2002 (Box 1, Folder 12-15)
- Allen Ginsberg Quotes and Letters (To and From), 1982-1993 (Box 1, Folder 16-17)
- Logos, 2003-2004 (Box 1, Folder 18-19)
- Emails and Key Articles, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- E.K.'s Student Action Union Folder, 1989-2005 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Amiri Baraka Poet Laureate Issue, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- E.K. Prose, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Melville House Publishing, includes reviews of Poetry after 9/11, 2001-2002 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Review of Alicia's [?] Book, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
- PEN, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Gregory Corso, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Poems for The Nation, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Abbie Hoffman 2000 Stuff (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Poetry Reading Posters NYC, 1993-2003 (Box 1, Folder 30-31)
- Poetry Posters NYC, late 1990s-2000 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Jack Hirschman Letters, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- NJ Contemporary Poets Anthology, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Promo Sheets for SPACE, undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Originals for Poetry and Music Flyers, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Elizabeth (Liz) Swados, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- "In the end every machine breaks down!" Poster, undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Letters from Carroll Terrell, 1990-1997 (Box 1, Folder 39)
- St. Mark's Talk, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Dissertation Proposal, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Rutgers Poetry Conference, 1987-1995 (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Williams Paper, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Miscellaneous Correspondence, 2002-2005 (Box 1, Folder 44-47)
- E.K. articles and Letters on Housing, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 48)
- Allen Ginsberg Posthumous Information, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 49)
- Arts Convention Project, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 50-51)
- Miscellaneous Correspondence, 2005-2006 (Box 1, Folder 52-54)
- Miscellaneous Correspondence, 2004-2006 (Box 1, Folder 55-56)
- E.K.'s Abbie Hoffman Folder including Abbie Hoffman Activist Foundation, 1986-1995 (Box 1, Folder 57-60)
- Mark Bradley information, 1990-1996 (Box 1, Folder 61-62)
- Essays I've written or started or letters to the editor or other letters about poetry or politics, 1988-1995 (Box 1, Folder 63)
- Photographs, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Great Miscellaneous from Ginsberg, Hoffman, Tom Waits, 1980-2001 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Writing by Eliot Katz for National Law Center on Homelessness and Poverty, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- National Law Center on Homelessness and Poverty (NLCHP) (Final Writings), 2005-2007 (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
- Poems with Music with Russell Branca, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Jason Shinder Project, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 7-8)
- Interesting Articles, 2002-2007 (Box 2, Folder 9-10)
- Tom Hayden Book, 2005-2007 (Box 2, Folder 11-12)
- Astorians for Peace and Justice (AFPJ), 2007 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Allen Ginsberg and East Village, 1988-2007 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- List of Poetry Journals Published in, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Scrapbook, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Signs for Rally NYC, 2017 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Drafts for Trump Artwork Piece, 2017 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Letters from Well-Known Writers and Activists, 1984-1995 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Newspaper clippings, Poetry and Event Posters, Correspondence, and Writing, 1983-2000 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Literary and Political Letters from E.K., 1990s (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Letters from People for Archives, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Amiri Baraka File (Regarding hiring issue), 1990-1996 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Letters from People to me regarding Poetry or my Poetry, 1988-1993 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Drafts of 2017 Poem about Trump (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Drafts of Health Poem, undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Rutgers Poetry Contest, 1997-04 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Letters, 1980s-1990s (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Letters from People, early 1980s (Box 2, Folder 29-30)
- Miscellaneous Poetry Items (Example: Nation article), 1989-1990 (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Other People's Quotes about my Poetry, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 32)
- Kearns - William Carlos William, Pound, 1991-1993 (Box 2, Folder 33-35)
- Kaplan- Papers (Adorno and Welfare), 1992 (Box 2, Folder 36)
- Articles that include my quotes regarding Politics, 1989-1993 (Box 2, Folder 37)
- Letters and Reviews regarding SPACE, 1989-1991 (Box 2, Folder 38)
- Eric Drooker, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 39)
- Davidson- Grad Papers, 1990-1992 (Box 2, Folder 40-41)
- Francis Combes, 1991-1996 (Box 2, Folder 42-43)
- Current and Immediate Project, 1992-1993 (Box 2, Folder 44)
- Wilhelm Reich and Blake Paper, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 45)
- Andy Clausen, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 46)
- File for Protest Poetry Anthologies for French, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 47)
- Photo Album, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Posters from Readings, 1982-1997 (Box 3, Folder 2-3)
- Principles of Unity for the Private Health Insurance Must Go Coalition (PHIMGC), 2007-2010 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- E.K. Manuscript Revisions for 'A LETTER TO ALLEN' with Notes, 2013-05 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Occupy Wall Street (O.W.S.) Posters and a Poem for O.W.S. by Eliot Katz, 2011 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Youth Dies Daily Eliot, undated (Box 4)
- Naropa and San Fran- Carl Rakosi, 2003-01-2004 (Box 4)
- Off the Page #8 with Eliot Katz (Back Up Copy), 1996-01-18 (Box 4)
- Conversations/ Channer - Time Warner Cable NYC - Guest: Eliot Katz and Andy Clausen, 2004-08-24 (Box 4)
- Off the Page #8 with Eliot Katz and Adam Bernstein (First Half Only), 1996-01-18 (Box 4)
- E. Katz COMPLETE Cafe Newz, 1994-09-28 (Box 4)
- Eliot Katz The Poetry Project, 2002-11-11 (Box 4)
- Eliot Katz with Russell Branca @ St Marks, 2008-03-12 (Box 4)
- Eliot Katz reads his poems, while Russell Branca plays his bass, 2006-04-09-2006-09-22 (Box 4)
- Eliot Katz Reads while Russell Branca Plays Bass, Artists for Humanity Concert, Live @ Community Church of NYC, 2006-04-09 (Box 4)
- E. Katz @ JMP, 2007-06-19 (Box 4)
- Eliot Katz reads his poems, while Russell Branca plays his bass, 2006-04-09-2006-09-22 (Box 4)
- Eliot Katz Reads while Russell Branca Plays Bass, Artists for Humanity Concert, Live @ Community Church of NYC, 2006-04-09 (Box 4)
- Astorians for Peace and Justice, 2007 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- "Something New (Jersey)" Poster, 2014 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Activist Projects, 1995-2012 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Anti-war Posters, circa 2004 (Box OS009, Folder 1)